can you
describe the nature of the relationship
between you and your own mind the CH in
any other way than what we have been
describing it so
far your own terms your own descriptions
your own
designations and then we can see what
comes out of
it so said an island so if you're doing
things in order to find
fulfillment or
accomplishment externally um it's a bit
externally um it's a bit
like being lost at in like an ocean in
the sense of it's endless there like
there's no end to to that
direction um well in contrast to that
the other
direction it's always there it's
always the
stable ground yeah yeah that's what one Su says
ground yeah yeah that's what one Su says
but um yeah
um yeah
and I suppose that also that contrast in
the sense of there being this stable
ground as opposed to like drowning like
this um when you
um when you
see that you're doing it for the an yeah
I'm using the animal again you're doing
it
yeah you're not doing it for for finding
accomplishment there you're doing it
to tame to
um to establish yourself
upon well to clarify yeah to to to for
that Clarity that Clarity is the thing
which means that you're not drowning
it's the it means that
you're you like no matter what happens
there is
um well safety in the sense that yeah
I'm not going to yeah go towards those
things that are going so what's
um what would be another
way of describing
that withdrawal from Multiplicity
unification or composure yeah exactly
yeah so it would be that
um unifying of the Mind in a sense of um
well in a sense of composure in a sense
of
Sam which again you know as we repeat
millions of times it's not the result of
concentration it's a result of
withdrawal from the
multiplicity you know the that talks
about the suit the perceptions of
diversity would have subsided and is
established upon the perception of unity
I the perception of that one gness of of
of an elevated space or a safe space or
a space that does not partake to the
ocean but that space is constantly being
bombarded by the hindrances by your own
thoughts and then by your own your own
depending on how you attend to your own
thoughts that are coming up is whether
that space would be um uncovered or
obstructed so there are varying degrees
to
which that Clarity is I mean absolutely
yeah there is more and more and more
but the the safety begins with the first
gen that's the safety I mean you might
feel relatively safe before that but the
fact is that you could that you still
could swim along with the hindrances if
you're careless means you're not truly
safe safe like the waves could still
pick you up from the shore and drag you
back
in so that's why like one shouldn't get
complacent
yeah I saw it as looking after my little
sister and you know there was that
similar kind of pressure and
responsibility that you have you feel
this thing looking at you learning from
you you know and you got it miring
everything you do you know you know
she's just you know just my sister it's
not my
child but I'm still resp you know she's
still learning she's still looking at me
at myov so it's like and so you know a
lot of parents are so it's the
relationship that I'm feeling that it's
a good description of it's the parent
and child and you know because of that
child and you know because of that
pressure that a parent would feel the
responsibility I think that's why a lot
of people just ignore you know kind of
ignore their minds and don't just don't
to look there don't to see what it's
doing don't want to take responsibility
and that's why lots of children get
abandoned in the in the world you know
uh so I think it's the same kind of
relationship really that of because the the child is
really that of because the the child is
mind is
malleable you know it's it can be
shaped so that mind is can be shaped and
you can be like 10 years 20 years but it
still has that nature of being able to
be shaped so even though it's encrusted
with whatever with habits and so on you
can still shape it unlike a yeah it
always remains the mind of a child that
way yeah but unless it matures finally
yeah but for that you need to mature
yeah so and only maturity is a giving up
of sensuality you know yeah so in the
suit with because that's what keeps it
childish basically and if it hasn't got to that
basically and if it hasn't got to that
point
well uh yeah another um good aspect of
that similar is similar is
that
see you know your child is not you like
a parent obviously you know it's no I'm
not my child but at the same time cannot
not identify with it
child with their child it's it's
impossible not to and that's exactly the
relationship between you and your CH
it's like even as I said people with
zero like taming or restraint or
withdrawal do have a sense of oh you
know Heart Wants What heart wants type
of thing or you know like um you can't
help but like my mind can't help but
want this or not want that I'm just like
I can't do anything about it so they're
aware it's a separate thing from their
own decision making capacities that
often overrides their own decisions and
reason even if they tell themselves well
no this is bad for me but I can't stop
doing it but at the same time there is
absolutely no recognition of any other
way of relating with it other than
identification oh Heart Wants What I
what heart wants but that's mine heart
that's me I am
that and they would often
prioritize see for example say say
reason tells you oh it's bad for
me I I don't want it I've been thinking
about it I've been reflecting and it's
like I really need to give this up but
you still have your chitt still craves
for it cuz it's still under the Habit
Under the Influence so to
speak and people would experience that
conflict they would experience that
discrepancy but they would take the
chitter side as more real than the
reason side so it would be like I know
it's so bad but the fact that there is
still this craving means I am the one
who wants it and that's why then they
sort of remain conflicted and remain
going back to it which is like the
nature of any addiction obviously uh but
actually there is no reason for you to
uh emphasize what chitt wants more than
what your reason tells you except not
wanting to endure the pain of it yeah so
a screaming
child screams to get what he wants and
you can't bear it because emotionally
you think you're torturing it or or
scarring it you must and then you just
you're just under the pressure of of of
it screams and then you give in and now
you convey the message that that's how
it will get what he wants I'll just
pressure you and scare you more until
you give me what I want and then I leave
you alone until there's something else
that I want so you're never really alone
you become enslaved simply by not
wanting to deal with
it and that's where that identification
would be coming from as
well by want to deal with it by giving
into it you basically start overlooking
it and then although you know it's not
you who really wants this who because I
know it's but I don't really want it I
hate it but there is still craving for
it you still go back to it and you still
think it's you who is doing that it's
like no you are just the one giving into
that so that's why without the sense
restraint first having been
first having been
practiced to contain it there is no
amount of insight or reason that will make you
of insight or reason that will make you
Prevail in that
sense first you just need to have a hard
know to the UNH wholesome
things yes so if a parent is
not setting an example to their own
child with their own
behavior no amount of telling their
child how to behave
would would convey the right message
because they first see how you're
behaving so you can be saying one thing
but if you're doing another that's what
they're going to see and say we you
could be trying to reason but yeah if
you still want and act
out and not even experience that
conflict between hold on I don't want
this but there is craving for it okay so
that's what needs to be undone if you're
just going along with
it because you prefer the path of less
resistance then what well that is the
message you're conveying so you can say
no no no stop but it's obvious you don't
really mean
it CU otherwise you would make the
effort to
stop that also like kind of create kind
of an incorr pattern for the mind
because you say yes you say no but
anyway you give in so you cannot learn
anything at some point yeah then it
basically the Mind learns that it
doesn't matter what you say
because you'll give into a pressure so
it's not taking you seriously exactly
what a child would do like you can be
shouting at it but it sees what you
really mean because the way you behave
so it's like it's not going to take you
seriously first time maybe it was scared
but then it realized n this is just
noise and then he learns how to do what
he wants to
do that's like that example you gave
with the
learning to how to convey a message to
it is not in this sort of direct I'll
just tell it this what it sees is what
you do so like in the example you gave
was more kind more direct was like you
can be speaking all of this but what
it's picking your body langage what
yeah yeah can you can be telling your
cheetah to not
resist to
unresisted while you're craving for it
so it's like well what do you think J
will be doing then you need to stop
craving for it
yourself yes impressionable it's like
through your actions so you you can tell
your kid to you know work hard in your
life and hard you know smoking playing
video games and telling your child you
know to take life seriously seriously
don't become like me that's exactly
what's going to happen you know but then
you you're working hard you're showing
that and you're just picking that up
yeah yeah exactly eventually he does the
same you
know so yeah that's exactly like you
want your Chet to turn
away from centrality from ill will from
hindrances from things that cause it
suffering you need to turn away from it
first you stop giving in you need to
stop delighting in it yourself relishing
it wishing for
it planning it craving for it and then J
can eventually get the message as well any
well any
other this side of the room
I was kind of struggling to come up with
something I've always kind of seen the
mind as this kind of very
vague just Cloud basically
um so at first when you came up with a
wild animal
simile it it was a bit it's as if it was
too kind of too
palpable for me it was too like almost
too relatable maybe mhm
solid yeah
[Music] but
uh but also in a way it was quite nice
because it's as if it creates space
between oh yeah for sure yourself and
and cuz that's the necessary step really
like say like what we just talk about
child the example of that yeah one of
the main reasons a p a parent would not
be disciplining their child or teaching
the right things even if they know they
should is cuz they're overly basically
personally identify with it and with its
feelings and with its moods or whatever
else and it's like that make you makes
you lose perspective so see I know
reasonably that saying no to my child
will be a good thing for them it will be
a beneficial for them but I will also
feel their pain when I say that to them
thus I can't say it because to to me the
avoiding that pain is more important so
it's just to personified two personal
involved and uh and you lose perspective
on account of it you recognize this is
factually for my welfare and for its
welfare otherwise we are both
done recognizing that
space Oh no no it's like I have a say in
this in the same sense I would have a
say in raising a child or taming a wild
animal and um although technically it's
still optional you don't have to do it
you don't have to do anything you
realize well it's pretty much the least
optional thing really if you think in
terms of what's beneficial for you and
for the animal in the long run that's
like this is the only thing that they
would qualify for beneficial everything
else is secondary to
that but yeah like people would not see
that space in between they would not
see they would be either to identify
with it too
mystified you know my mind it's this
this great entity too personally
involved in the same sense you would be
with your child uh all of that results
in a loss of
perspective uh perspective that would be
revealing the danger of that situation
like the cow her similar in the suta
like you know if the if the person
responsible for keeping an eye on the
cows while they're
grazing forgets that they're going to
beat him and imprison him if the cows go
and eat other people's
Fields he he won't pay attention to
where where they eat and what they do
and um most people choose to forget
those things because well it seems
optional that's how it present itself
because there is no immediate uh
punishment that you feel and when you do
you don't make the association between
the two um and then also because see like if
two um and then also because see like if
I live under a constant threat of I
could get in trouble well that's very
unpleasant for me that's not a nice
state of mind and plus these animals are
now agitated CU I don't let them meat
where they want so as I said naturally a
person would choose a path of less
resistance and then the death and the
punishment would accumulate and when it
comes you will have nothing but to just
cry about
it with the SIM of like your sister
there's also
like we were talking on Telegram about
like how you know the otherness
of of the mind is like the otherness of
people and like slightly less though
yeah yeah slightly less cuz you are
still well you you don't want to person
cuz it's not a full person that's the
point it's important yeah you don't want
to just think oh it's just another
person basically cuz it isn't that's the
thing and the same sense a young child
it's like as he was saying it's it's
it's the mind is still
malleable so it's not like a full
personality or the animal you could
personify it you could give it more than
it is but the fact is if it's another
person it kind of becomes like a a
complete thing like the way people
relate with each other it's like well
I'm I you are you you do your thing I do
my thing same oh my mind is has its own
mind it does its own I'll do my own
thing it's like no no no no no it's the
child or the animal so it's you can't
have that degree of Independence as you
would from another person person yeah so
that's why I was saying before in the
previous talk it's important to not
overly personify it on the other hand
you don't want to underp personify it
either saying oh it's just chemical
brain processes and responds to stimul
and has no consciousness of its own it's
like well it does because it makes its
own choices obviously that you pressured
by so it's like there is that degree of
autonomy of
CH but if you add too much to it you
won't see it if you take away too much
from it you won't see it
either because again the goal is to tame
the child or teach it rightly or tame
the animal if
animal if
you're overly emotionally invested you
will not you will lose perspective or if
you just say well I wash my hands with
you you do your own thing well you might
feel Freer for that period of time but
Freer for that period of time but
factually the goal of training that
child is not complete yeah that's the
opposite so you can't really just just
okay well I'll just do my thing you go
on your own not with your you can do
that with other people but with your no
you're just going to stay where you are
and the result of that attitude will be
you're not taming
it is it where like the kind of
aesthetic practice come from like this
kind of one thing to push CH away and
pretty much yeah yeah have a clean cut
through all of this so it doesn't even
have to come up so I don't have to deal
with it that's exactly what it is the
the the um those aere self-mortification
practices sometimes doing such practices
in relation to Cheta can be beneficial
and that's what would have said well let
those who want to do those practices do
them not make them mandatory because it
will actually result in oh okay I'll
stick to this I don't see my mind
anymore it's not my problem it's like no
it remains your problem you're just
ignoring it
now and sometimes it will be even sort
of counterintuitive even to your own
values very much so when it comes to
like clarifying and outlining mind
rightly as I said you shouldn't be
overly um emotionally invested but you
shouldn't be trying to get rid of it or
sort of dismiss it either and sometimes
in order to do neither of those things
you realize oh so what I just have to
eat milk porridge now like a hous holder
but that's not right by any aesthetic by
any self-respecting sort of sumoner
That's Not
Right But then the buha realiz well
actually it's not about that it's not
about where my values are currently
it's about direct input from the Mind
from the chitt how does this and then he
realized oh if I don't do this I will
not be able to train
it cuz the mind is too
weak too too invisible basically too
beaten down by everything else he was
doing so yeah that's again that's what
saying like and even in the sutas the
Buddha would often when he came to these
aesthetic practices and how much and
where is the line he said well you
realize the line you have the broad line
things never to be done obvious the
precepts and so on but then all de
sudden was like he was dependent on
where the mind was sometimes eating milk
rice will obscure your mind depending on
where your intention was sometimes it
will reveal it depending on where your
intention to not it
was but for that you need to see the
mind and that's the reference
and when you have that reference then
you can train happily day and night as
it s to say because you realize oh it's
this is the input no external but how
can you do that that's not you shouldn't
be doing that you shouldn't be eating
rice and that's exactly what his former
friends and companion they were
disgusted with him oh he reverted to
luxury and they left him but if he was
caring about that about his peers
approving of him he would have never
become the Buddha if he was caring about
the tradition that he's been following
established culture he would have never
become the Buddha because none of that
has a mind as a reference point it's
just circumstantial involvement of
everything and nothing
really that's why keep saying like you
know the the framework is the
presets everything within that if it's
tighter or looser well that should be
determined individually every single time on the
individually every single time on the
basis of where your mind is and why
you're doing it
for I think yeah it's good to emphasize
as well like every single time because
even let's say milk rice the same thing
it's very so easy to say oh I find I
always want this particular thing I'll
just give it up yeah and it's much
harder to notice that on some days
it can be rooted in craving and pressure
then you don't do it and on another
occasion or actually it's not and now
you shoulda allow but I still won't do
it and people would fall in their TR
like yeah but it doesn't matter thus I
won't do it cuz it doesn't really matter
and it's like well it's true but see you
could say the same in Reverse it doesn't
really matter so why don't you do
it it doesn't really matter so I won't
do it so it just becomes a justification
to just keep tighten ening enen out of
some as I said perceived sense of Duty
that forces you to
like well that forces you to raise your
child properly you can't just oh it was fine
properly you can't just oh it was fine
eating this yesterday I can just give it
to to it today without having to look at
it or think about it that's exactly what
it becomes or it wasn't fine eating
yesterday thus I will keep forbidding it
because again it's easier to just adhere
to the view now
that came out of it and you could
reasonably recognize every single time
where the intentions are rooted what
state of the child is it is it unruly
crying screaming having a fit to get
what he wants
no if it isn't then now it's maybe even
a bit depressed or something okay give
it now to like to loosen up a bit within
as I said what was um what was defined
is presets you don't you don't go past
that line that's too
much but it's it's a constant work in
that sense you have constantly have to
keep an eye on it then you constantly
have to be checking in and and and and
monitoring which way it takes and that's
just too
cumbersome because at the same time I
have this view of it now that if I just
keep this as a rule to
it it will be the same effect minus me
having to deal with it and the point is
it won't have the same effect it's not
learning it's not learning exactly it's
not learning that's the the simil of the of
learning that's the the simil of the of
the deer her like when when the group of
athetic recognized oh yeah this is all
the bait and Mar snare so they Shine the
bait go on the mountain say no to
everything and then they begin to starve
basically and when they do return to
stuff to eat they still don't
distinguish where the bait is so they
get again trapped M Mar and then the final
again trapped M Mar and then the final
deer her was the one that learned how to
eat around the bait every single
time not to eat it
unwarily and that's exactly it so it's
like every single time the reference
point should be the state of aitt for
whether to act or not act whether it's
beneficial whether it's un
beneficial and that's the the the whole
training in the nutshell really the
whole practice of Jan it's exactly that
he just taming the cheetah
rightly not choking it and as fixating
it and not letting it run
loose until it's basically stabilized on
the safe ground and it recognizes that
and that's the result is CH via VIA from
the UNH wholesome States from the pulls
from the pressures from the hindrances
from the obstructions
so when the Buddha says in the Su go
monks and practice Jana that's what he
means doesn't mean go monks and and do
some meditation technique because it
would be at the end of such sutas see
they would talk about the sutta about
purifying your mind uh not giving into
UNH wholesome States instruct the monks
in all these details and then tell them
okay now you heard this now go and do
the Jana if jna was something completely
Jana if jna was something completely
different from that he wouldn't have
said it at the end of that context
and then you realize at the end of
different contexts of types of
purification and how to attend to things
he would address go now and do the Jana
do the Jana basically means do this mind
training on account of these context I'm
providing you that's why it was unique
to him unique to the Buddhist
practice and that's why exactly the
result in overcoming the five hindrances
when the unruly child becomes fully
disciplined understanding seeing for
itself what's good for it when the wild
animal is fully tamed
obedient pretty much knows what you
think without even having to do it to
say it or tell tell it to
do and then you both live happily that's
like the pleasant abiding here and
now and the only thing that can disturb
that is if you start carelessly going
back to to S sound smell tast statues
like they s to say they then indirectly
start disturbing the animal again cuz it
wasn't completely um well it wasn't completely
completely um well it wasn't completely
freed so you want
to calm it withdraw it from the UN
wholesome stabilize it on the elevated
safe ground the island but then protect
it there don't think now cuz you will
think oh I can relax now cuz it's true
you can relax but not in regard to the
bait you can Rex to the animal but don't
forget the bait is still
there so although you can probably
handle it more than you used to you are
still grabbing onto the hooks and traps
unnecessarily and that is agitating the
animal maybe not as much as it used to
but it's still agitating
it so there's absolutely no reason to do
it yeah that's the priority then yeah
that's
yeah that's right the thorough
bread will never be alone from the horse
trainer can't get rid of the horse
trainer initially he
might think or assume that the safety
would be the greatest safety would be if
there is no horse trainer he has to come
to terms to to accept that he'll never
be alone from the horse trainer the only
way out from the whip of the horse
trainer is to tame his behavior not not
remove the whole
trainer so it's and same like in the in
the reverse order similar we gave it's
like the animal is watching you the mind
is basically seeing only what you do so
in that sense you never Le from it and
that's why you can never be yourself
fully cuz you're always undermined by
the other